<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Genasi from Monsters of the Multiverse</name>
		<update version="0.0.1">
			<file name="race-genasi.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/GEIIOW/FaleriaCore/refs/heads/main/core/faleria/races/race-genasi.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Genasi" type="Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACE_GENASI">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">“What came first, the ocean or rain? Neither. There are corners of our reality that no man is meant to explore, for in them lies a power that would devour us all. Myth tells us of six realms that were created alongside Basalos, and would later be used to help create our world. They are the root of the air we breath, the water we drink and, most importantly, our magic! Genasi are the ultimate biproduct of these elemental realms, a marriage of mortel men and primordial ideals! They might hold the knowledge I have been seeking, for they are the closest mortals to true innate power.”</p>
			<p>- Y. Mageshell, Manyhals of Death.</p>
			<p>Genasi are closely connected to the elements of the world that surrounds them. Being the children of the elements means they hold power over those same elements. Some genasi use their connection to better the communities that embrace them, while some turn the natural world against mortals of lesser descent. Genasi are a rare sight in the world, having few communities of their own, but make an impact wherever they reside as they are the descendants of divine beings, which can mold their outlook towards the world for the better or for the worse.</p>
			
			<h4>GENASI NAMES</h4>
			<p>Genasi tend to either use the naming conventions of their country of origin or adopt nicknames used to describe them by the people closest to them while they were being raised. Traditional genasi names capture their elemental heritage, such as Candlelight, Tremor, Coral, Sky, Zap and Mage</p>
			
			<h4>GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Genasi seem to be born with an array of elemental abilities.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability score increse.</em></strong> Your Constitution score increases by 2.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> Genasi reach adulthood at around 20 years old and live about 130 years.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> Genasi stand between 4’9 and 7’2 feet tall and average about 150 pounds. Your size is Medium.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your walking speed is 30 feet.</p>	
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Elemental Ward.</em></strong> As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.</p>
			<p>Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal type). Any subsequent spells gained through mortal type must be cast with the ability score you chose.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read, and write one language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for your character and another dependant on your mortal subtype.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal subtypes.</em></strong> Six elemental lefkadas gave way to six types of genasi: Air, Arcana, Earth, Fire, Lightning and Water Genasi. Choose one of these subtypes.</p>	
			
			<h4>MORE INFORMATION</h4>	
			<p>For more details and updates, visit: https://homebrewery.naturalcrit.com/share/Jfg5UUWU-4nz</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Adran, Aelar, Aramil, Arannis, Aust, Beiro, Berrian, Carric, Enialis, Erdan, Erevan, Galinndan, Hadarai, Heian, Himo, Immeral, Ivellios, Laucian, Mindartis, Paelias, Peren, Quarion, Riardon, Rolen, Soveliss, Thamior, Tharivol, Theren, Varis</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Adrie, Althaea, Anastrianna, Andraste, Antinua, Bethrynna, Birel, Caelynn, Drusilia, Enna, Felosial, Ielenia, Jelenneth, Keyleth, Leshanna, Lia, Meriele, Mialee, Naivara, Quelenna, Quillathe, Sariel, Shanairra, Shava, Silaqui, Theirastra, Thia, Vadania, Valanthe, Xanaphia</set>
			<set name="names" type="family">Amakiir, Amastacia, Galanodel, Holimion, Ilphelkiir, Liadon, Meliamne, Nai'lo, Siannodel, Xiloscient</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}} {{family}}</set>
		</setters>

		<rules>
			<stat name="constitution" value="2" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />	
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />		
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Genasi)" supports="Standard" />
			<select type="Sub Race" name="Genasi Subtype" supports="Genasi" />
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Elemental Ward (Racial Trait)" supports="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ELEMENTAL_WARD_INTELLIGENCE|ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ELEMENTAL_WARD_CHARISMA|ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ELEMENTAL_WARD_WISDOM" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Elemental Ward" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ELEMENTAL_WARD">
		<description>
			<p>As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.</p>
			<p>Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal type). Any subsequent spells gained through mortal type must be cast with the ability score you chose.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
	</element>

	
	<element name="Intelligence" alt="Elemental Ward" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ELEMENTAL_WARD_INTELLIGENCE">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Elemental Ward" action="reaction" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				Your spellcasting ability is Intelligence. As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_ABSORB_ELEMENTS" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Charisma" alt="Elemental Ward" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ELEMENTAL_WARD_CHARISMA">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Elemental Ward" action="reaction" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				Your spellcasting ability is Charisma. As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_ABSORB_ELEMENTS" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Wisdom" alt="Elemental Ward" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ELEMENTAL_WARD_WISDOM">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Elemental Ward" action="reaction" usage="1/Long Rest" >
			<description>
				Your spellcasting ability is Wisdom. As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_ABSORB_ELEMENTS" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Air Genasi-->
	<element name="Air Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_SUB_RACE_AIR_GENASI">
		<supports>Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Air genasi descend from the elemental plane of air, Aithéros, specifically from the Djin. Their mood is one of extremes, being as calm a summer breeze or as aggressive as a hurricane. Where they stand, wind as strong as their emotions follows, either lightly tousling their hair and clothes or angrily blowing it upwards.</p>
			<p>Air genasi typically have light blue skin, hair, and eyes.</p>
	
			<h4>AIR GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As an air genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Improvement.</em></strong> Your Dexterity score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Unending Breath.</em></strong> You can hold your breath indefinitely while you're not incapacitated.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Thunder Resistance.</em></strong> You have resistance to thunder damage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Moonsoon.</em></strong> You know the gust cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the feather fall spell with this trait, without material components. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the fly spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast feather fall or fly with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak Galish.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="dexterity" value="1" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_GALISH" />
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_THUNDER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MOONSOON" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_UNENDING_BREATH" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Unending Breath" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_UNENDING_BREATH">
		<description>
			<p>You can hold your breath indefinitely while you're not incapacitated.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can hold your breath indefinitely while you're not incapacitated.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Moonsoon" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MOONSOON">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <strong>gust</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>feather fall</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>fly</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>feather fall</strong> or <strong>fly</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				You know the <strong>gust</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast <strong>feather fall</strong> spell with this trait. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>fly</strong> spell with this trait. Once you cast <strong>feather fall</strong> or <strong>fly</strong> with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_GUST" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FEATHER_FALL" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FLY" level="7" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Arcana Genasi-->
	<element name="Arcana Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_SUB_RACE_ARCANA_GENASI">
		<supports>Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Arcana genasi descend from the elemental plane of arcana, Períaptos, specifically from the Alamite. They tend to be chaotic people, like the wildest of magic. Wherever they go, a trail of arcane weave always follows, like ethereal silk that is connected to their bodies.</p>
			<p>Arcana genasi typically have purple skin, white or purple hair, and purple or dark blue eyes.</p>
	
			<h4>ARCANA GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As an arcana genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Improvement.</em></strong> Your Intelligence score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Arcane eye.</em></strong> You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) rolls made to see through magical illusions.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Magic Resistance.</em></strong> You have advantadge on saving throws against spells.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Magic Flow.</em></strong> You know the prestidigitation cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the identify spell with this trait without material components. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the dispel magic spell with this trait. Once you cast identify or dispel magic with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak Arcanian.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="intelligence" value="1" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_ARCANIAN" />
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_RESISTANCE_MAGIC" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MAGIC_FLOW" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ARCANE_EYE" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Magic Resistance." type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_RESISTANCE_MAGIC">
		<description>
			<p>You have advantadge on saving throws against spells.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have advantadge on saving throws against spells.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Arcane Eye" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ARCANE_EYE">
		<description>
			<p>You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) rolls made to see through magical illusions</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) rolls made to see through magical illusions</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Magic Flow" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MAGIC_FLOW">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <strong>prestidigitation</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast <strong>identify</strong> spell with this trait. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>dispel magic</strong>  spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>identify</strong> or <strong>dispel magic</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				You know the <strong>prestidigitation</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast <strong>identify</strong> spell with this trait. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>dispel magic</strong> spell with this trait. Once you cast <strong>identify</strong> or <strong>dispel magic</strong> with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PRESTIDIGITATION" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_IDENTIFY" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_DISPEL_MAGIC" level="7" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Earth Genasi-->
	<element name="Earth Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_SUB_RACE_EARTH_GENASI">
		<supports>Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Earth genasi descend from the elemental plane of earth, Gaiágros, specifically from the Dao. Stubborn and resilient, they tend to be unbothered by much like a rock. Some earth genasi grow minerals and crystals on various parts of their bodies, making beautiful jewls or patterns.</p>
			<p>Earth genasi typically have deep brown or black skin, and hair, and eyes of the colour of any gemstone.</p>
			
			<h4>EARTH GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As an earth genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Improvement.</em></strong> Your Strength score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Earth Walk.</em></strong> You can move across difficult terrain without expending extra movement if you are using your walking speed on the ground or a floor.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Acid Resistance.</em></strong> You have resistance to acid damage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Tectonic Plating.</em></strong> You know the mold earth cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the earth tremor spell with this trait. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the erupting earth spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast earth tremor or erupting earth with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak Soddish.</p>
		</description>	
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="strength" value="1" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_FLYSODDISH" />
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_ACID" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_WALK" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_TECTONIC_PLATING" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Earth Walk" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_WALK">
		<description>
			<p>You can move across difficult terrain without expending extra movement if you are using your walking speed on the ground or a floor.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can move across difficult terrain without expending extra movement if you are using your walking speed on the ground or a floor.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Tectonic Plating" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_TECTONIC_PLATING">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <strong>mold earth</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>earth tremor</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>erupting earth</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>earth tremor</strong> or <strong>erupting earth</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				You know the <strong>mold earth</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>earth tremor</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>erupting earth</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>earth tremor</strong> or <strong>erupting earth</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>	
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_MOLD_EARTH" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_EARTH_TREMOR" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_ERUPTING_EARTH" level="7" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Fire Genasi-->
	<element name="Fire Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_SUB_RACE_FIRE_GENASI">
		<supports>Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Fire genasi descend from the elemental plane of fire, Pyragrós, specifically from the Efreet. Their mood is energetic and lively, with no time to waste on the downsides of lives, relentless and quick like a forest fire. Where they are, cinders can be seen fluttering out of their skin and hair into the air that surrounds them, slightly projecting more body heat.</p>
			<p>Fire genasi typically have fire red or ash grey skin, with yellow, orange or red hair and eyes.</p>
			
			<h4>FIRE GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As an fire genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Improvement.</em></strong> Your Intelligence score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Smokescreen. </em></strong> You can see in lightly obscured areas within 30 feet of you as if it wasn’t obscured and in heavily obscured areas as if it were lightly obscured.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Fire Resistance. </em></strong> You have resistance to fire damage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Combustion.</em></strong> You know the control flames cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the burning hands spell with this trait. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the fireball spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast burning hands or fireball with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak Blazanese.</p>
		</description>	
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="intelligence" value="1" />				
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_SMOKESCREEN" />			
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_FIRE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_COMBUSTION" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_BLAZANESE" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Combustion" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_COMBUSTION">
		<description>
				You know the <strong>control flames</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>burning hands</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>fireball</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>control flames</strong> or <strong>fire ball</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				You know the <strong>control flames</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>burning hands</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>fireball</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>control flames</strong> or <strong>fire ball</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_CONTROL_FLAMES" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_BURNING_HANDS" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FIREBALL" level="7" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Water Genasi-->
	<element name="Water Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_SUB_RACE_WATER_GENASI">
		<supports>Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Water genasi descend from the elemental plane of water, Ýdoros, specifically from the Marid. Water genasi tend to be fluctuate between calm, collected and a go with the current attitude and a stressed and overthinking attitude, pulling every thought to them like a whirlpool. They always look and feel as if they have just got out of the water, occasionally dripping water onto the floor.</p>
			<p>Water genasi typically have blue or green skin, hair and eyes.</p>
			
			<h4>WATER GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As an water genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Improvement.</em></strong> Your Wisdom score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Water Adept.</em></strong> You breathe air and water and have a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Cold Resistance.</em></strong> You have resistance to cold damage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Beyond the shore.</em></strong> You know the shape water cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the create or destroy water spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the sleet storm spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast create or destroy water or sleet storm with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak Hydralese.</p>
		</description>	
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="wisdom" value="1" />				
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_ADEPT" />			
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_COLD" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BEYOND_THE_SHORE" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_HYDRALESE" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Water adept" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_ADEPT">
		<description>
			<p>You breathe air and water and have a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You breathe air and water and have a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="speed:swim" value="speed" bonus="base" />
		</rules>		
	</element>
	<element name="Beyond the shore" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BEYOND_THE_SHORE">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <strong>shape water</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>create or destroy water</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>sleet storm</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>create or destroy water</strong> or <strong>sleet storm</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
		</description>		
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				You know the <strong>shape water</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>create or destroy water</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>sleet storm</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>create or destroy water</strong> or <strong>sleet storm</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_SHAPE_WATER" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CREATE_OR_DESTROY_WATER" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SLEET_STORM" level="7" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Lightning Genasi-->
	<element name="Lightning Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_SUB_RACE_LIGHTNING_GENASI">
		<supports>Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Lightning genasi descend from the elemental plane of lightning, Kelôngros, specifically from Ztyvil. They are surprising, flashy and loud, letting everyone know they have entered every room they enter, much like lighting confiscating the sky to itself during a storm. When they move, small sparks emmanate from their bodies.</p>
			<p>Lighting genasi typically have blueish yellow skin, hair and eyes.</p>
			
			<h4>LIGHTNING GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As an lightning genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Improvement.</em></strong> Your Dexterity score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Light Speed.</em></strong> You have a movement of 35 feet. Additionally, you can take the Dash or Disengage action as a bonus action.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Lightning Resistance.</em></strong> You have resistance to lightning damage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Eye of the Storm. </em></strong> You know the shape water cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the create or destroy water spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the sleet storm spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast create or destroy water or sleet storm with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak Laitvian.</p>
		</description>	
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="dexterity" value="1" />				
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LIGHT_SPEED" />			
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_LIGHTNING" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_EYE_OF_THE_STORM" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_LAITVIAN" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Light Speed" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LIGHT_SPEED">
		<description>
			<p>You have a movement of 35 feet. Additionally, you can take the Dash or Disengage action as a bonus action.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus action">
			<description>You have a movement of 35 feet. Additionally, you can take the Dash or Disengage action as a bonus action.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="speed" value="35" bonus="base" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Eye of the Storm" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_EYE_OF_THE_STORM">
		<description>
				<p>You know the <strong>lightning lure</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>longstrider</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>haste</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>longstrider</strong> or <strong>haste</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
		</description>		
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				You know the <strong>lightning lure</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <strong>longstrider</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>haste</strong> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <strong>longstrider</strong> or <strong>haste</strong> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_WOTC_TCOE_SPELL_LIGHTNING_LURE" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_LONGSTRIDER" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_HASTE" level="7" />
		</rules>
	</element>
</elements>
