<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Genasi from Monsters of the Multiverse</name>
		<update version="0.0.1">
			<file name="race-genasi.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/GEIIOW/FaleriaCore/refs/heads/main/core/faleria/races/race-genasi.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Genasi" type="Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACE_GENASI">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">“What came first, the ocean or rain? Neither. There are corners of our reality that no man is meant to explore, for in them lies a power that would devour us all. Myth tells us of six realms that were created alongside Basalos, and would later be used to help create our world. They are the root of the air we breath, the water we drink and, most importantly, our magic! Genasi are the ultimate biproduct of these elemental realms, a marriage of mortel men and primordial ideals! They might hold the knowledge I have been seeking, for they are the closest mortals to true innate power.”</p>
			<p>- Y. Mageshell, Manyhals of Death.</p>
			<p>Genasi are closely connected to the elements of the world that surrounds them. Being the children of the elements means they hold power over those same elements. Some genasi use their connection to better the communities that embrace them, while some turn the natural world against mortals of lesser descent. Genasi are a rare sight in the world, having few communities of their own, but make an impact wherever they reside as they are the descendants of divine beings, which can mold their outlook towards the world for the better or for the worse.</p>
			
			<h4>GENASI NAMES</h4>
			<p>Genasi tend to either use the naming conventions of their country of origin or adopt nicknames used to describe them by the people closest to them while they were being raised. Traditional genasi names capture their elemental heritage, such as Candlelight, Tremor, Coral, Sky, Zap and Mage</p>
			
			<h4>GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Genasi seem to be born with an array of elemental abilities.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability score increse.</em></strong> Your Constitution score increases by 2.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> Genasi reach adulthood at around 20 years old and live about 130 years.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> Genasi stand between 4’9 and 7’2 feet tall and average about 150 pounds. Your size is Medium.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your walking speed is 30 feet.</p>	
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Elemental Ward.</em></strong> As a reaction, you can cast the absorb elements spell once per long rest.</p>
			<p>Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal type). Any subsequent spells gained through mortal type must be cast with the ability score you chose.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read, and write one language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for your character and another dependant on your mortal subtype.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal subtypes.</em></strong> Six elemental lefkadas gave way to six types of genasi: Air, Arcana, Earth, Fire, Lightning and Water Genasi. Choose one of these subtypes.</p>	
			
			<h4>MORE INFORMATION</h4>	
			<p>For more details and updates, visit: https://homebrewery.naturalcrit.com/share/Jfg5UUWU-4nz</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Adran, Aelar, Aramil, Arannis, Aust, Beiro, Berrian, Carric, Enialis, Erdan, Erevan, Galinndan, Hadarai, Heian, Himo, Immeral, Ivellios, Laucian, Mindartis, Paelias, Peren, Quarion, Riardon, Rolen, Soveliss, Thamior, Tharivol, Theren, Varis</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Adrie, Althaea, Anastrianna, Andraste, Antinua, Bethrynna, Birel, Caelynn, Drusilia, Enna, Felosial, Ielenia, Jelenneth, Keyleth, Leshanna, Lia, Meriele, Mialee, Naivara, Quelenna, Quillathe, Sariel, Shanairra, Shava, Silaqui, Theirastra, Thia, Vadania, Valanthe, Xanaphia</set>
			<set name="names" type="family">Amakiir, Amastacia, Galanodel, Holimion, Ilphelkiir, Liadon, Meliamne, Nai'lo, Siannodel, Xiloscient</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}} {{family}}</set>
		</setters>

		<rules>
			<stat name="constitution" value="2" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />	
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />		
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Genasi)" supports="Standard" />
			<select type="Sub Race" name="Genasi Subtype" supports="Genasi" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Air Genasi-->
	<element name="Air Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_SUB_RACE_AIR_GENASI">
		<supports>Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Air genasi descend from the elemental plane of air, Aithéros, specifically from the Djin. Their mood is one of extremes, being as calm a summer breeze or as aggressive as a hurricane. Where they stand, wind as strong as their emotions follows, either lightly tousling their hair and clothes or angrily blowing it upwards.</p>
			<p>Air genasi typically have light blue skin, hair, and eyes.</p>
	
			<h4>AIR GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Improvement.</em></strong> Your Dexterity score increases by 1.</p>
			<p>As an air genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Unending Breath.</em></strong> You can hold your breath indefinitely while you're not incapacitated.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Thunder Resistance.</em></strong> You have resistance to thunder damage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Moonsoon.</em></strong> You know the gust cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the feather fall spell with this trait, without material components. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the fly spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast feather fall or fly with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak Galish.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="dexterity" value="1" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_GALISH" />
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_THUNDER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MOONSOON" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_UNENDING_BREATH" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Unending Breath" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_UNENDING_BREATH">
		<description>
			<p>You can hold your breath indefinitely while you're not incapacitated.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can hold your breath indefinitely while you're not incapacitated.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Moonsoon" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MOONSOON">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <i>gust</i> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <i>feather fall</i> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <i>fly</i> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <i>feather fall</i> or <i>fly</i> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>
				You know the <strong>gust</strong> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast <strong>feather fall</strong> spell with this trait. Starting at 7th level, you can also cast the <strong>fly</strong> spell with this trait. Once you cast <strong>feather fall</strong> or <strong>fly</strong> with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
			</description>
		</sheet>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_XGTE_SPELL_GUST" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FEATHER_FALL" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FLY" level="7" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Earth Genasi-->
	<element name="Earth Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_SUBRACE_EARTH_GENASI">
		<supports>MOTM Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Tracing their ancestry to dao, the genies of the Elemental Plane of Earth, earth genasi inherit dao's steadfast strength and control over earth.</p>
			<p class="indent">An earth genasi's skin can be the colors of stone and earth or a human skin tone with glittering sparkles like gem dust. Some earth genasi have lines marking their skin like cracks, either showing glimmering gemlike veins or a dim, yellowish glow. Earth genasi hair can appear carved of stone or crystal or resemble strands of spun metal.</p>
			<h4>EARTH GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As an earth genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creature Type.</em></strong> You are a Humanoid.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your walking speed is 30 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Darkvision.</em></strong> You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You discern colors in that darkness only as shades of gray.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Earth Walk.</em></strong> You can move across difficult terrain without expending extra movement if you are using your walking speed on the ground or a floor.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Merge with Stone.</em></strong> You know the <i>blade ward</i> cantrip. You can cast it as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</p>
			<p class="indent">Starting at 5th level, you can cast the <i>pass without trace</i> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast that spell with this trait, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast it using any spell slots you have of 2nd level or higher.</p>
			<p class="indent">Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells when you cast them with this trait (choose when you select this race).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_EARTH_WALK" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_MERGE_WITH_STONE" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Earth Walk" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_EARTH_WALK">
		<description>
			<p>You can move across difficult terrain without expending extra movement if you are using your walking speed on the ground or a floor.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can move across difficult terrain without expending extra movement if you are using your walking speed on the ground or a floor.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Merge with Stone" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_MERGE_WITH_STONE">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <i>blade ward</i> cantrip. You can cast it as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</p>
			<p class="indent">Starting at 5th level, you can cast the <i>pass without trace</i> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast that spell with this trait, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast it using any spell slots you have of 2nd level or higher.</p>
			<p class="indent">Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells when you cast them with this trait (choose when you select this race).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_BLADE_WARD" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PASS_WITHOUT_TRACE" level="5"/>
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Spellcasting Ability (Merge with Stone)" supports="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_MERGE_WITH_STONE_INTELLIGENCE|ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_MERGE_WITH_STONE_WISDOM|ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_MERGE_WITH_STONE_CHARISMA" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Intelligence" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_MERGE_WITH_STONE_INTELLIGENCE">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Merge with Stone">
			<description>You know the blade ward cantrip. You can cast it as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action {{proficiency}} times, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Intelligence.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the blade ward cantrip. You can cast it as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action {{proficiency}} times, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest. &#13;
			You can cast the pass without trace spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast that spell with this trait, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast it using any spell slots you have of 2nd level or higher. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Wisdom" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_MERGE_WITH_STONE_WISDOM">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Merge with Stone">
			<description>You know the blade ward cantrip. You can cast it as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action {{proficiency}} times, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Wisdom.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the blade ward cantrip. You can cast it as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action {{proficiency}} times, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest. &#13;
			You can cast the pass without trace spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast that spell with this trait, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast it using any spell slots you have of 2nd level or higher. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Charisma" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_EARTH_GENASI_MERGE_WITH_STONE_CHARISMA">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Merge with Stone">
			<description>You know the blade ward cantrip. You can cast it as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action {{proficiency}} times, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Charisma.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the blade ward cantrip. You can cast it as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action {{proficiency}} times, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest. &#13;
			You can cast the pass without trace spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast that spell with this trait, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast it using any spell slots you have of 2nd level or higher. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<!--Fire Genasi-->
	<element name="Fire Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_SUBRACE_FIRE_GENASI">
		<supports>MOTM Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Descended from efreet, the genies of the Elemental Plane of Fire, fire genasi channel the flamboyant and often destructive nature of flame. They show their heritage in their skin tones, which can range from deep charcoal to shades of red and orange. Some bear skin tones common to humanity but with fiery marks, such as slowly swirling lights under their skin that resemble embers or glowing red lines tracing over their bodies like cracks. Fire genasi hair can resemble threads of fire or sooty smoke.</p>
			<h4>FIRE GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As a fire genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creature Type.</em></strong> You are a Humanoid.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your walking speed is 30 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Darkvision.</em></strong> You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You discern colors in that darkness only as shades of gray.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Fire Resistance.</em></strong> You have resistance to fire damage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Reach to the Blaze.</em></strong> You know the <i>produce flame</i> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <i>burning hands</i> spell with this trait. Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the <i>flame blade</i> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <i>burning hands</i> or <i>flame blade</i> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent">Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells when you cast them with this trait (choose when you select this race).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_FIRE_RESISTANCE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_REACH_TO_THE_BLAZE" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Fire Resistance" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_FIRE_RESISTANCE">
		<description>
			<p>You have resistance to fire damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_FIRE" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Reach to the Blaze" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_REACH_TO_THE_BLAZE">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <i>produce flame</i> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <i>burning hands</i> spell with this trait. Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the <i>flame blade</i> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <i>burning hands</i> or <i>flame blade</i> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent">Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells when you cast them with this trait (choose when you select this race).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PRODUCE_FLAME" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_BURNING_HANDS" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FLAME_BLADE" level="5" />
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Spellcasting Ability (Reach to the Blaze)" supports="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_REACH_TO_THE_BLAZE_INTELLIGENCE|ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_REACH_TO_THE_BLAZE_WISDOM|ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_REACH_TO_THE_BLAZE_CHARISMA" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Intelligence" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_REACH_TO_THE_BLAZE_INTELLIGENCE">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Reach to the Blaze">
			<description>You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Intelligence.</description>
			<description level="3">You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast the burning hands spell with this trait once per long rest. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast burning hands and flame blade spells with this trait component once each per long rest, without requiring a material. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Wisdom" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_REACH_TO_THE_BLAZE_WISDOM">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Reach to the Blaze">
			<description>You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Wisdom.</description>
			<description level="3">You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast the burning hands spell with this trait once per long rest. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast burning hands and flame blade spells with this trait component once each per long rest, without requiring a material. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Charisma" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_FIRE_GENASI_REACH_TO_THE_BLAZE_CHARISMA">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Reach to the Blaze">
			<description>You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Charisma.</description>
			<description level="3">You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast the burning hands spell with this trait once per long rest. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the produce flame cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast burning hands and flame blade spells with this trait component once each per long rest, without requiring a material. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<!--Water Genasi-->
	<element name="Water Genasi" type="Sub Race" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_SUBRACE_WATER_GENASI">
		<supports>MOTM Genasi</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Water genasi descend from marids, aquatic genies from the Elemental Plane of Water. Water genasi are perfectly suited to life underwater and carry the power of the waves inside themselves.</p>
			<p class="indent">Their skin is often shades of blue or green, sometimes a blend of the two. If they have a human skin tone, there is a glistening texture that catches the light, like water droplets or nearly invisible fish scales. Their hair can resemble seaweed, waving as if in a current, or it can even be like water itself.</p>
			<h4>WATER GENASI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As a water genasi, you have the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creature Type.</em></strong> You are a Humanoid.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your walking speed is 30 feet, and you have a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Acid Resistance.</em></strong> You have resistance to acid damage.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Amphibious.</em></strong> You can breathe air and water.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Call to the Wave.</em></strong> You know the <i>acid splash</i> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <i>create or destroy water</i> spell with this trait. Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the <i>water walk</i> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <i>create or destroy water</i> or <i>water walk</i> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent">Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells when you cast them with this trait (choose when you select this race).</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Darkvision.</em></strong> You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You discern colors in that darkness only as shades of gray.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed:swim" value="innate speed" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_ACID_RESISTANCE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_AMPHIBIOUS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_CALL_TO_THE_WAVE" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Acid Resistance" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_ACID_RESISTANCE">
		<description>
			<p>You have resistance to acid damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_ACID" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Amphibious" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_AMPHIBIOUS">
		<description>
			<p>You can breathe air and water.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can breathe air and water.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Call to the Wave" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_CALL_TO_THE_WAVE">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <i>acid splash</i> cantrip. Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the <i>create or destroy water</i> spell with this trait. Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the <i>water walk</i> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast <i>create or destroy water</i> or <i>water walk</i> with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.</p>
			<p class="indent">Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells when you cast them with this trait (choose when you select this race).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ACID_SPLASH" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CREATE_OR_DESTROY_WATER" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_WATER_WALK" level="5" />
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Spellcasting Ability (Call to the Wave)" supports="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_CALL_TO_THE_WAVE_INTELLIGENCE|ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_CALL_TO_THE_WAVE_WISDOM|ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_CALL_TO_THE_WAVE_CHARISMA" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Intelligence" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_CALL_TO_THE_WAVE_INTELLIGENCE">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Call to the Wave">
			<description>You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Intelligence.</description>
			<description level="3">You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast the create or destroy water spell with this trait, once per long rest. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			You can also cast create or destroy water spell and the water walk spell with this trait once each per long rest, without requiring a material component. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Wisdom" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_CALL_TO_THE_WAVE_WISDOM">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Call to the Wave">
			<description>You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Wisdom.</description>
			<description level="3">You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast the create or destroy water spell with this trait, once per long rest.  You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			You can also cast create or destroy water spell and the water walk spell with this trait once each per long rest, without requiring a material component. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Charisma" type="Racial Trait" source="Monsters of the Multiverse" id="ID_WOTC_MOTM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_GENASI_CALL_TO_THE_WAVE_CHARISMA">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet alt="Call to the Wave">
			<description>You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for this spell is Charisma.</description>
			<description level="3">You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			You can cast the create or destroy water spell with this trait, once per long rest.  You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</description>
			<description level="5">You know the acid splash cantrip. &#13;
			You can also cast create or destroy water spell and the water walk spell with this trait once each per long rest, without requiring a material component. You can also cast these spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level. &#13;
			Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
</elements>
