<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Zailm</name>
		<update version="0.0.1">
			<file name="race-zailm.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/GEIIOW/FaleriaCore/refs/heads/main/core/faleria/races/race-zailm.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Zailm" type="Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACE_ZAILM">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">“My work may not yet be complete, but these creatures show just how grandiose my purpose is. After years of work, I’ve finally made substancial progress when it comes to using the power of souls. The men and women that were part of my latest test, of trying to power a dead body with only the power of a soul, have been reanimated as something more than they were before. While they still don’t seem to have memories of their previous life, they have become stronger, some have become faster and more resilient. Nothing less than a complete success.”</p>
			<p>- Y. Mageshell, Manyhals of Death.</p>
			<p>The Zailm are reborn warriors who can’t get a grasp of their past. Originating from Zeiloryn, these once mortal humanoids scattered throughout Faleria in seach of themselves. While their past may be lost to them, their future is full of potencial due to their mind being null of previous abilities and their new enhanced physiology.</p>

			<h4>Immortalized mortals</h4>
			<p>Zailm don’t all hail from a shared mortal type. There are those who seem to have been human, others who are of a smaller stature and resemble halflings or gnomes and even those who tower over the tallest of mortals. Their state of decay is irrelevant to their functionallity, so it’s possible to see some Zailm who are missing limbs, jaws or much more of their bodies, while others are in pristine condition, only being recognised as Zailm due to their shared grayish skin tone.</p>
			<p>Zailm are thought ageless, meaning they don’t age, but their mind will start to detiorate after a certain amount of time due to having too many memories accumulated.</p>

			<h4>The valley of death</h4>
			<p>Many of those who get reanimated as Zailm completely lose their mind, turning into yet another angry and feral undead creature, while the ones who manage to retain their sanity tend to present a high degree of functionality and capacity for civility. Though often times prosecuted without just cause, many zailm are sought as hired swords when times get tough.</p>
			<p>Ostracized from certain parts of the world, some of these reborn abominations chose to gather and make a kingdom of their own in Manyhal where they now reside. Since creating their kingdom of Vlandaer, the zailm have found a way to recreate their creators formula to create more of their own kind, giving them an ever growing army.</p>
			<p>Despite this military power, it is far more common for Vlandaer to be on the defensive rather than on the attack as they only sought refuge from a world that didn’t accept them. Something that may be bound to change.</p>

			<h4>A shapeless kind</h4>
			<p>Zailm is more of a title than a descriptor of a person. When we talk about a human we know they have, usually, 4 appendages, a head and a torso, not the zailm though. These beings have been stitched together piece by piece, making some unrecognizable. All zailm have grayish skin or fur but not all have both of their arms and legs. Some don’t have their lower jaw, some have horns on their head, some have them somewhere else. Some look as if they aren’t deceased at all, others make you wonder how they’re moving at all. How the population treats zailm depends on how grotesque they appear to be.</p>

			<h4>Zailm names</h4>
			<p>It is to expect that a type of people robbed of their past and thrown into the world would name themselves whatever came to mind, but that’s not the case. For the zailm that are part of Vlandaer, the names they have adopted are a tribute to the great empire’s capital city that once stood just north of their own border, so they choose names that we would call greco-romanic. For those outside of that kingdom they can either choose their own name based on the culture they inhabit or, on very rare cases, remember their name from when they were alive.</p>

			<h4>Zailm traits</h4>
			<p>Zailm seem to have been reborn with an assortment of new abilities.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one or increase three different ability scores by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> It is unkown for how long the source of you new life can support it. Zailm don’t age, but will resume rotting when they reach 0 hit points or if their connection to their source of new life is broken.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creature Type.</em></strong> You are an Undead.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> The size of Zailm is dependent on their previous life and there doesn’t seem to exist a medium of height nor weight. Your size is either Small or Medium.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your base walking speed is 30 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Sunlight Sensitivity.</em></strong> The dark arts that made you into a Saphir have made it so direct sunlight is toxic towards you. You have disadvantage on attack rolls and on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight when you, the target of your attack, or whatever you are trying to perceive is in direct sunlight.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ethereal Sight.</em></strong> You can see 60 feet into the Ethereal Plane when you are on the Material Plane and vice versa.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Undead Fortitude.</em></strong> If damage reduces you to 0 hit points, you must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, you drop to 1 hit point instead.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Glimpses of the Past.</em></strong> Immediately after rolling a skill check with which you are proficient, you may roll a d6 and add the resulting roll to the skill check’s total. You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages. </em></strong> You can speak, read and write two languages of your choice.</p>
			
			<h4>MORE INFORMATION</h4>	
			<p class="indent"><strong>For more details and updates, visit:</strong> https://homebrewery.naturalcrit.com/share/9fezuqPyoY0n</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Adran, Aelar, Aramil, Arannis, Aust, Beiro, Berrian, Carric, Enialis, Erdan, Erevan, Galinndan, Hadarai, Heian, Himo, Immeral, Ivellios, Laucian, Mindartis, Paelias, Peren, Quarion, Riardon, Rolen, Soveliss, Thamior, Tharivol, Theren, Varis</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Adrie, Althaea, Anastrianna, Andraste, Antinua, Bethrynna, Birel, Caelynn, Drusilia, Enna, Felosial, Ielenia, Jelenneth, Keyleth, Leshanna, Lia, Meriele, Mialee, Naivara, Quelenna, Quillathe, Sariel, Shanairra, Shava, Silaqui, Theirastra, Thia, Vadania, Valanthe, Xanaphia</set>
			<set name="names" type="family">Amakiir, Amastacia, Galanodel, Holimion, Ilphelkiir, Liadon, Meliamne, Nai'lo, Siannodel, Xiloscient</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}} {{family}}</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_INTERNAL_RACIAL_TRAIT_TYPE_UNDEAD" />	
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Ability Score Improvement (Zailm)" supports="ID_ASI_RACE_ZAILM1|ID_ASI_RACE_ZAILM2" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Zailm)" supports="Standard" number="2" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SUNLIGHT_SENSITIVITY" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_ETHEREAL_SIGHT" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_UNDEAD_FORTITUDE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GLIMPSESOFTHEPAST" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one" type="Ability Score Improvement" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_ASI_RACE_ZAILM1">
		<description>
			<p>You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one or increase three different ability scores by 1.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<compendium display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +2 (Zailm)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Zailm)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI"/>
		</rules>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Increase three different ability scores by 1" type="Ability Score Improvement" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_ASI_RACE_ZAILM2">
		<description>
			<p>You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one or increase three different ability scores by 1.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<compendium display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Zailm)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" number="3"/>
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Ethereal Sight" type="Vision" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_VISION_ETHEREAL_SIGHT">
		<description>
			<p>You can see 60 feet into the Ethereal Plane when you are on the Material Plane and vice versa.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can see {{ethereal sight:range}} feet into the Ethereal Plane when you are on the Material Plane and vice versa.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="ethereal sight:range" value="60" bonus="base" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Undead Fortitude" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_UNDEAD_FORTITUDE">
		<description>
			<p>If damage reduces you to 0 hit points, you must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, you drop to 1 hit point instead.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>
				<p>If damage reduces you to 0 hit points, you must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, you drop to 1 hit point instead.</p>
			</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Glimpses of the Past" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GLIMPSESOFTHEPAST">
		<description>
			<p>Immediately after rolling a skill check with which you are proficient, you may roll a d6 and add the resulting roll to the skill check’s total. You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="{{proficiency}}/Long Rest">
			<description>Immediately after rolling a skill check with which you are proficient, you may roll a d6 and add the resulting roll to the skill check’s total. You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

</elements>
