<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Human</name>
		<update version="0.0.1">
			<file name="race-human.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/GEIIOW/FaleriaCore/refs/heads/main/core/faleria/races/race-human.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Human (Faleria)" type="Race" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_FALERIA_RACE_HUMAN">
	<supports>Human</supports>
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">“They are a plague upon this world. These little pests can not only survive anywhere in this world but also thrive wherever they settle. Their kind has given great contributions to my field of study though, I’ll give them that. Much like goblins, humans are born as dumb as rocks. Gross little balls of pure potential, but, unlike goblins, they live long enough to actually make a difference. I met a brilliant human once. He was kind hearted and dedicated. Achieved what took me 90 years in just 10. They can be great. It still saddens me that he didn’t approve of my methods.”</p>
			<p>- Y. Mageshell, Manyhals of Death.</p>
			<p>Humans are everywhere in Faleria, from the coldest mountains, to the driest deserts. While most other mortals are born with special skills or abilities, with wit or cunning, humans are born with naught. Where as other mortals are born with advantages, humans need to work for theirs and there lies humanities power. Humans are born to choose their fate and, when that fate doesn’t suit them, they will adapt to the world or adapt the world to them.</p>

			<h4>The first men</h4>
			<p>It is said that humans were one of the three primary Kássian races, the first to emerge in the world of Faleria, being created alongside Dwarves and Elves by Yivor, Myllad and Kássia as servants in their godly works. Humans were created for Kássia, Queen of the gods, to explore Faleria in search of the Vigil gods. After they had succeeded in this quest, their numbers had grown exponentially. Some humans had built communities, kingdoms and empires.</p>
			<p>Humans have changed a lot through the generations and the world with them. They take pride in their ancestors and their legacy. Stories are told of heroes who conquered great beasts or kings who truly earned their crown. Despite being the ones who live the least out of the Kássians, humans survive in memory for much longer.</p>

			<h4>Human traits</h4>
			<p>Human nature presents them with a versatile set of abilities.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one or increase three different ability scores by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> Humans reach adulthood in their late teens and tend to live less than a century.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> Humans vary widely in height and build, from barely 5 feet to well over 6 feet tall. Regardless of your position in that range, your size is Medium.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your base walking speed is 30 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Feat.</em></strong> You gain one feat of your choice.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Quick learner.</em></strong> Whenever you gain an Ability Score Improvement you can increase one ability score by 1, regardless of your choice of ability score improvement type.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Malleable.</em></strong> You gain half proficiency in a skill of your choosing. This half proficiency may be changed after finishing a long rest.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read and write three languages of your choice.</p>
			
			<h4>MORE INFORMATION</h4>	
			<p>For more details and updates, visit: https://homebrewery.naturalcrit.com/share/lOIlRW2-1m6i</p>

		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Adran, Aelar, Aramil, Arannis, Aust, Beiro, Berrian, Carric, Enialis, Erdan, Erevan, Galinndan, Hadarai, Heian, Himo, Immeral, Ivellios, Laucian, Mindartis, Paelias, Peren, Quarion, Riardon, Rolen, Soveliss, Thamior, Tharivol, Theren, Varis</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Adrie, Althaea, Anastrianna, Andraste, Antinua, Bethrynna, Birel, Caelynn, Drusilia, Enna, Felosial, Ielenia, Jelenneth, Keyleth, Leshanna, Lia, Meriele, Mialee, Naivara, Quelenna, Quillathe, Sariel, Shanairra, Shava, Silaqui, Theirastra, Thia, Vadania, Valanthe, Xanaphia</set>
			<set name="names" type="family">Amakiir, Amastacia, Galanodel, Holimion, Ilphelkiir, Liadon, Meliamne, Nai'lo, Siannodel, Xiloscient</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}} {{family}}</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM"/>
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base"/>	
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Human)" supports="Standard" number="3" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Ability Score Improvement (Human)" supports="ID_ASI_RACE_HUMAN1|ID_ASI_RACE_HUMAN2" />		
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_QUICK_LEARNER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MALLEABLE" />
			<select type="Feat" name="Feat (Human)" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one" type="Ability Score Improvement" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_ASI_RACE_HUMAN1">
		<description>
			<p>You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one or increase three different ability scores by 1.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<compendium display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +2 (Human)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Human)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI"/>
		</rules>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Increase three different ability scores by 1" type="Ability Score Improvement" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_ASI_RACE_HUMAN2">
		<description>
			<p>You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one or increase three different ability scores by 1.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<compendium display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Human)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" number="3"/>
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Quick Learner" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_QUICK_LEARNER">
		<description>
			<p>Whenever you gain an Ability Score Improvement you can increase one ability score by 1, regardless of your choice of ability score improvement type.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
		<p>Whenever you gain an Ability Score Improvement you can increase one ability score by 1, regardless of your choice of ability score improvement type.</p>
		</sheet>	
	</element>

	<element name="Malleable" type="Racial Trait" source="Yozolin's Lost Tome" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_MALLEABLE">
		<description>
			<p>You gain half proficiency in a skill of your choosing. This half proficiency may be changed after finishing a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="Long Rest">
		<p>You gain half proficiency in a skill of your choosing. This half proficiency may be changed after finishing a long rest.</p>
		</sheet>
	</element>

</elements>
